(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine.
And today we've got an upper intermediate
level lesson for you all about money.
- That's right, we are trading money.
We're actually negotiating
in this very popular topic
nowadays, the whole
foreign exchange market.
- Okay, so we're talking about currency,
which is the money of different countries.
For example, the currency of Ecuador is--
- The US dollar.
(laughing)
- Yeah, yeah, hard to believe, but true.
I'll tell you all about it later.
- Okay, well the currency of
America is also the US dollar.
So with that in mind, let's
listen to today's dialogue.
(upbeat music)
- Hey John, I haven't seen you in ages.
What's new?
What have you been up to?
Pete, nice to see you.
Well, on top of the norm, you
know, life and kids and work,
I've actually gotten
into doing some trading.
Trading?
You big guy?
What are you trading?
Currencies.
Currencies?
As in euros, dollars, pounds, and rupees?
It's called Forex, foreign exchange.
The great thing about it is that I
don't have to invest a huge amount.
I put in a margin deposit and then I can
buy and sell up to 100 times that much.
I don't understand, you're
buying and selling money?
You got it.
Just last night, I made 150 US dollars.
Last night?
Yeah, it's a 24 hour market.
I'd bought some Rem in
Bea earlier at a low asking
price, but last night it
appreciated drastically.
So I made a split second decision and
sold all of my RMB at an amazing bid.
I've also done some
trading with Swiss francs
in Australian dollars
and Hong Kong dollars.
I've made some good profits,
but I've also suffered some losses.
It depends on a lot of factors,
just like any other market.
In total, I've made about 500
US dollars in the past few months.
If you're kidding, I'm on.
Where do I sign up?
All right, we're back.
So this guy is trading
currencies as we heard.
And well, we're going
to talk about a lot of the
specific vocab that he
used about this topic.
So why don't we take a look at some
of those now in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Well, the first thing I
think we should talk about
is one of the first
things that he says,
actually, Peter says, I
haven't seen you in ages.
I haven't seen you in ages, right?
So obviously he hasn't seen him in a
long time, and that's what in ages means.
That's right.
So we haven't seen each other in ages.
So what other ways can we
use in ages or the word ages?
Well, you could actually
say it's been ages.
So that means it's been a long time.
It's been a long time or we
haven't gone out for ages.
OK, so then you can
use it with four for ages.
Four ages in ages.
So the key word here is
ages, which means a long time.
Long time.
OK.
And well, he hasn't seen him in ages.
And the guy's like, well, you know what?
I've actually gone into trading.
So that means he's
started doing some trading.
Right.
Now, trading is a very
broad word because you
can trade, as in this
case, currencies, which
is basically to buy
and sell currencies.
But you could also trade stocks, right?
You can trade stocks or even people
that are involved in import export.
They are involved in trading.
Trading.
So basically trading is
buying and selling something.
Right, so you're trading.
You are exchanging a product
for money or money for a product.
But the difference is you're
not actually making any products.
Right.
OK, so that's called trading.
You're not really manufacturing anything.
You're just exchanging
goods and services and money.
All right.
So that's for trading now moving on.
He was explaining how the
foreign exchange market works.
And he says, I don't have
to invest a huge amount.
I put in a margin deposit.
And then I can buy and sell
up to 100 times that much.
So Marco, here's the question,
what is a margin deposit?
Because a deposit is
basically money that
you put invest somewhere
or that you pay in.
Right.
Well, basically, a margin
deposit is like a percentage.
So he basically puts in a
percentage of what he intends to buy.
So for example, a margin deposit
of $1,000 might be $1 per $10.
OK, so maybe it's $10.
You're talking about a 1% margin.
Exactly.
So that's what he means
by a margin deposit.
And that's why he explains that you
don't have to have a large amount of money
in order to trade in the
foreign exchange market.
You just put in a margin deposit.
And then you can work around that.
Well, it sounds pretty easy.
But then he explains
some more details about it.
And it gets to be a little
bit more complicated.
That's right.
He explained about how he makes money
and how he bought some Chinese lemon b.
And then he sold it because
it appreciated drastically.
So he bought it when it was cheap.
And he sold it when it was expensive.
So the price changed.
Right.
So this kind of price change
when something goes from
cheap to expensive, it's called
appreciating, appreciation.
So the verb is to appreciate.
It's very different from
using it in the sense
of you appreciate someone, right?
Like, oh, I really appreciate you.
Yeah, no, it's very different.
We could say this about
most goods or investments.
For example, my parents
bought a house in 1970.
And the value of the house has
really appreciated over the last 40 years.
So now the value is much, much greater.
And actually just mentioning
it while we're on the topic
to appreciate, as you say, is
something becomes more expensive.
The opposite when something becomes cheaper
or maybe the value goes
down is to depreciate.
Depreciate so that D at the
beginning means it's going down.
Right.
OK.
And moving on to our last
word for language takeaway.
So when he was talking
about selling the Chinese
currency, he said that he
sold it at an amazing bid.
OK, let's talk about bid here.
B-I-D, bid.
What does this mean?
So to bid is to place
an offer for something.
OK, so for example, at an auction
when someone is selling many old
objects or some art, I can bid $100.
Right.
And maybe someone doesn't accept my bid.
But if they do accept
my bid, then I pay for it.
Right.
So basically, a bid is
just another way of saying
an offer of you're
offering a certain amount
of money for that
product or that service.
And you see it a lot, for
example, on eBay, right?
That's right, so eBay is an
auction website, basically.
And someone who's selling
someone can see many, many bids.
And they select the best bid.
Exactly.
So that's what a bid is.
So that's all we have
for language takeaway.
Let's move on now to fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Marco, what have you been up to lately?
I never see you.
All right.
This is actually a very common sentence.
What have you been up to?
But most English learners don't
really understand what it means.
Well, this is a really interesting
point, because I say this all the time.
This is very native, very colloquial.
What have you been up to?
It's almost the same as saying what's up?
What's up, or where have you been recently?
What have you been doing recently?
Right.
How's your life?
So this part up to what
have you been up to?
It doesn't really say much
if you translate it literally.
But basically, it's what
have you been doing?
What have you been spending your time on?
So to be up to means
to do something, to do.
Right.
And there are many
other definitions of up to.
But in this case, what have
you been up to means that?
What have you been doing?
So next time you see a friend
you haven't seen in a week
or two, you can say,
what have you been up to?
Mm-hmm.
All right.
And John answers, well,
you know, on top of the norm,
five kids and work, that phrase
right there, on top of the norm.
Well, the norm here means the norm all.
That means basically normal life.
I've been working, I've
got my kids, my wife,
on top of the norm,
just life is normal.
Right.
So the norm or the wife,
kids, and work, on top
of that, I'm actually
gunning into trading, right?
So the normal situation, the normal life,
is wife, kids, and
work, and any saying on
top of that, I've
actually been doing this.
Exactly.
Okay.
And now moving on to
when he's explaining, again,
the market and the currencies,
he talked about an asking price.
Okay, asking price.
This is, remember we're talking about bids?
We could say that
someone has an asking price,
which is the price they
would like to receive
for an object or a service
that they are selling.
And so, for example,
I'm gonna sell my desk.
My asking price is a hundred
bucks, hundred dollars.
Maybe you don't wanna pay that much,
but my asking price is the
way that I'm gonna start.
That's how much I want for it.
Right.
So that's your asking price.
That's how much you ideally want
to sell it for, but you can negotiate.
You are willing to accept
maybe a lower offer.
Exactly.
Okay.
And what is our last phrase?
A split second decision.
This is really, really important.
These words go together very often.
Split second and decision.
Okay. So that basically means
that you made a very quick decision.
That's right.
Split second.
Very fast.
It's almost like it's less than a second.
And so a split second decision
means a decision in no time.
Very, very quick.
So we can actually mix split
second with other things, right?
For example, so maybe you can say he reacted
in a split second and avoided the crash.
Okay. So good for him.
He reacted quickly enough
to avoid the accident.
That's right.
Split second very fast, very quickly.
A split second decision, a
decision that was made very fast.
Okay.
So that's all we have for fluency builder.
When we go back, listen to
this dialogue one more time
and we'll be back to
talk a little bit more.
Hey, John, I haven't seen you in ages.
What's new?
What have you been up to?
Pete, nice to see you.
Well, on top of the norm, you
know, life and kids and work,
I've actually gotten
into doing some trading.
Trading?
You big guy?
What are you trading?
Currencies.
As in euros, dollars, pounds and rupees.
It's called Forex for an exchange.
The great thing about it is that I
don't have to invest a huge amount.
I put in a margin
deposit and then I can buy
and sell up to a
hundred times that much.
I don't understand, you're
buying and selling money.
You got it.
Just last night, I made one
hundred and fifty U.S. dollars.
Last night?
Yeah, it's a 24 hour market.
I'd bought some Rem
in B earlier at a low asking
price, but last night it
appreciated drastically.
So I made a split second decision and
sold all of my RMB at an amazing bid.
I've also done some
trading with Swiss francs
and Australian dollars
and Hong Kong dollars.
I've made some good profits,
but I've also suffered some losses.
It depends on a lot of factors,
just like any other market.
In total, I've made
about five hundred U.S.
dollars in the past few months.
You're kidding.
I'm on.
Where do I sign up?
So Marco, you have to explain this to me.
We're talking about currency today.
So every nation has a currency.
For example, in the dialogue,
we learn that India has rupees.
Pounds are in Britain, Britain has pounds,
and Australia has Australian dollars.
America has American dollars.
But you just said it earlier that
Ecuador has American dollars too.
That's right.
Actually, Ecuador went through a very
difficult economic situation in late 1998,
early 1999, where there
was a hyperinflation.
So basically, there was an inflation
that was very, very, very large.
So that means that the old
currency lost its value very fast.
Exactly.
So for example, if the currency
before an Ecuador used to be sucres.
So if 10 sucres was one dollar, all of a
sudden it was 50 sucres was one dollar.
Oh wow.
So, and it got to the point
where goods and services
went from 3,000 to a
dollar to 25,000 to a dollar.
Oh, okay.
So people have bags full of money,
and it's not really worth anything.
Exactly.
So what happened was the central bank
couldn't absorb this currency depreciation.
They couldn't really regulate prices.
Obviously, salaries were about the same,
so you have a lot less money comparatively.
And so the government
decided that there were
two options, either they
would follow Argentina's
example, what they did a couple
of years before, and set a fixed rate.
So, our Argentina,
it's three pesos to a
dollar, or we would just get rid of
our currency and just use US dollars.
So that's what they did, right?
They use US dollars, and now if you ever
travel to Ecuador, you will use US dollars.
The same exact bills that you use in
the US are the same exact bills in Ecuador.
So no need to exchange currency.
No need to exchange currency.
And that's why I guess there are many
factors that people say are a lot better.
For example, trading
has become a lot less
complicated because
now you're negotiating in
US dollars as in
everywhere else in the world.
But then other things, as you know,
not having a national currency also effect.
So there are a lot of things going
on, but it's an interesting topic.
Very interesting.
Well, so maybe for
those of you who are
listening, you could tell us about
your country and your currency.
What do you use?
What do you spend money on?
And do people buy and trade
currencies where you're from?
Exactly.
Even enlighten us with
the foreign, with the
exchange rate maybe,
usually it's a good question
to ask how much is a leader of
milk for how much is a haircut, right?
Because these are things
that everyone needs.
So the price doesn't change that much.
Exactly.
We're really curious to
know how inexpensive
or maybe very
expensive your country is.
So come to EnglishPod.com
and we'll see everyone there.
Bye.
[BLANK_AUDIO]